So, how is it?
Bagaimana ini?
Hang on. The radiator is still too hot.
Tunggu, Mas. Radiatornya masih panas.
Hurry up. We're late already.
Ayo cepat. Sudah telat ini.
I'll get scolded by the factory people!
Nanti saya dimarahi oleh orang pabrik!
-Come on, hurry up! Fix it quickly! -Yes, sir.
Ayo, cepat! Cepat!
Come on!
Ayo!
Get on!
Ayo, naik!
Chop-chop!
Cepat!
Come on, hurry! We're late! Come on!
Ayo, ayo cepat! Udah telat ini! Ayo!
Wait!
Tunggu!
How could you leave the leader behind?
Bagaimana sih? Pemimpin kok malah ditinggal?
Come on.
Ayo.
Wait, sir.
Tunggu, Mas.
-Thank you. -Fadhil, come here.
- Terima kasih. - Fadhil, di sini saja!
Okay.
Ya.
Just stand here.
Berdiri di sini saja.
Naning, I'm standing next to you, okay?
Dek Naning, aku di sebelahmu, ya?
If you feel sleepy,
Nanti kalau Dek Naning mengantuk,
you can rest your head on my strong shoulder.
'kan langsung bisa senderan di bahuku yang kokoh ini loh.
Okay?
Ya?
My shoulder was made just for you.
Bahuku ini tercipta hanya untukmu, loh, Dek.
Naning, don't turn down his offer.
Naning, jangan ditolak.
This is your chance to lean on an ancient statue.
Kapan lagi kamu senderan sama arca?
-What did you say? -I'm helping you.
Kok arca toh?
-Wati! -Come on!
- Wati! - Ayo berangkat!
Wait for me! Wait, sir!
- Nanti dulu! Nanti dulu, Mas! - Mas, sebentar!
Wait for me.
Tunggu!
Hendra, help me.
Mas Hendra. Tolong.
-You're coming? -I am.
- Kamu jadi ikut? - Jadi, Mas.
-In God's name. -Your mother gave her blessing?
- Bismilah. - Enggak apa-apa toh ibumu?
She finally did.
Enggak apa-apa, Mas.
I convinced Mother that I wanted to help you out.
Aku bicara dengan Ibu kalau aku mau bantu Mas Hendra kerja.
We're the ones getting married. I want to contribute to the cost.
Yang mau nikah kan kita, Mas,
Okay, then. Give that to me.
Ya sudah. Kemarikan itu.
Honey!
Mas!
Your hand.
- Tangannya. - Apa?
I know that smile.
Senyum-senyum. Ketawa-ketawa.
Now that your fiancée is coming.
Mentang-mentang calon istrinya ikut.
You must have dirty plans.
Pikiranmu ngeres pasti.
I suspect you two are going to--
Jangan-jangan kalian mau kumpul…
-Do some cowboy camping. -What the…
- Kumpul koboi. - Apa…
Shut your mouth!
Hei, diam!
You don't get it. Don't butt in.
Tidak mengerti apa-apa kok ikut-ikutan!
Going to sleep around?
Mau kumpul kebo, 'kan?
Watch your mouth!
Mulutmu!
-Honey, stop it. -I'll put you to sleep!
- Mas, hentikan. - Wajahmu itu kayak kebo!
Naning…
Naning…
Stop it.
Pegangan dong.
Be careful, Naning.
Hati-hati, Dek Naning.
Not me!
Bukan aku!
-Let's pray. -It was Endah.
- Berdoa dulu. - Endah.
Pray first.
Berdoa dulu.
Damn it!
Sialan!
You're drooling!
Liurmu itu loh!
Your drool smells rancid.
Kok bisa air liur seperti racun?
Why are you wiping it on me? Hey!
Hei! Kok malah dilap? Hei!
Calm down, will you?
Kenapa sih kamu?
Calm down? He's drooling all over me and it smells like a corpse.
Kenapa? Dia berliur, baunya seperti mayat walang sangit.
Just ignore it.
Ya sudah.
Don't overreact, Franky.
Enggak apa-apa sih, Franky.
I'll have to burn this shirt.
Tidak apa-apa? Bau liurmu itu loh.
Is that the factory?
Itu pabriknya?
Yes, that's the factory.
Ya, itu pabriknya.
It's unlike the ones on TV.
Enggak kayak di TV, ya?
Don't believe TV commercials.
Di TV itu kan iklan.
This is the real thing.
Ini pabrik sungguhan.
Those who have received their lodge numbers,
Yang sudah dapat nomor loji,
go straight to your assigned rooms.
langsung masuk loji masing-masing.
Dinner's ready.
Mari makan.
Finally!
Mari kita makan dulu.
Hey, miss. Come, join us.
Hei, Mbak. Ikut makan, Mbak.
-It's okay. -Sit.
- Enggak usah repot. - Duduk. Gak apa-apa. Ada banyak.
Thanks.
- Terima kasih, ya. - Ya.
We haven't been introduced.
Kita belum kenalan ya, Mbak?
-I'm Endah. -I'm Rani.
- Aku Endah. - Aku Rani, Mbak.
Nice to meet you, Rani.
- Salam kenal, Mbak Rani. - Rani.
I'm Naning. Please don't be shy around us.
Saya Naning. Nggak usah malu-malu kalau sama kita.
That's right.
Ya.
I'm Wati.
Aku Wati.
The three of us come from the same village.
Kami bertiga ini dari kampung yang sama, Mbak.
What is that sound?
Itu suara apa, ya?
I think it's the alarm to go to bed. It was explained earlier.
Kayaknya tanda sudah tidur.
Endah, what are you looking at?
Endah, lihat apa?
Let's eat.
Ayo makan dulu.
Come on.
Ayo.
Let's eat, Endah.
Ayo makan dulu, Endah.
Fine, I'm coming.
Ya.
Oh, my God.
Astagfirullahalazim.
Wati?
Wati?
Naning?
Naning?
Rani?
Mbak Rani?
I'm leaving, Wati.
Mbak Wati, aku duluan, ya.
-Okay. -See you.
- Duluan? - Ya.
Take care.
Hati-hati, ya.
Wati, where's Naning?
Lo, Wati, Naning mana?
That's the thing.
Nah itu.
Naning!
Naning!
Naning, don't take too long!
Naning, jangan lama-lama!
Or else we'll be late!
Nanti telat loh!
Yes. Coming.
Ya. Tunggu.
How pretty.
Cantiknya.
But of course.
Ya, jelas.
Who knows? Might meet the one here.
Siapa tahu dapat jodoh.
Only you can think like that.
Pikirmu saja.
Come on, then.
Ya sudah, ayo.
Cover up.
Tutup.
Naning, Wati, either of you went out last night?
Naning, Wati.
No.
Enggak.
Nope. Slept like a baby.
Aku sih enggak. Aku tidur.
Why do you ask?
Kenapa?
Nothing.
Enggak apa-apa.
I heard someone opening the door.
Aku dengar suara pintu dibuka.
I thought someone left our lodge.
Aku kira ada yang keluar.
I must have heard wrong.
Mungkin aku salah.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Naning.
Dek Naning.
You look so cute this morning.
Pagi-pagi kok udah manis banget.
Just like me when I was a baby.
Kayak aku pas masih kecil.
For those who arrived late yesterday, I'm Marni.
Untuk yang kemarin terlambat,
I'm in charge of the seasonal workers at this factory.
Saya yang bertanggung jawab atas pekerja musiman di pabrik ini.
This is Mr. Samin.
Di sini ada Mbah Samin.
We also have Rano and Karno, the security guards here.
Ada juga Rano dan Karno.
And the foremen who will oversee your work.
Dan ada mandor-mandor yang akan membantu mengawasi kerja kalian.
I must tell you about the curfew.
Ada yang ingin saya jelaskan soal jam malam.
You must've heard it last night.
Kalian pasti sudah dengar kemarin.
The sound of the slit drum after dusk
Suara pentungan
signifies the beginning of the yellow hours.
itu tanda jam kuning.
During the yellow hours,
Di saat jam kuning,
all workers have to be within the vicinity of their respective lodges.
semua buruh
And the sound of the steam whistle at 9:00 p.m.
Sementara suara peluit pabrik
signifies the beginning of the red hours.
itu artinya
During the red hours,
Pada jam merah ini,
you are not allowed to leave your lodges at all.
kalian dilarang keras
Keep this rule without any exception.
Dan peraturan ini tidak boleh dilanggar.
In three days, the milling will start.
Tiga hari lagi, penggilingan akan dimulai.
Now, please go with the foremen as they call your name.
Sekarang, silakan kalian ikuti mandor yang akan memanggil nama kalian.
The explanation about your tasks will be given at each post.
Dan penjelasan mengenai tugas masing-masing
Understand?
Begitu, ya?
-Let's start. -Yes, ma'am.
- Silakan dimulai. - Ya.
Listen carefully, all of you.
Dengarkan baik-baik, Mas, Mbak.
Listen for your name.
Dengar nama yang dipanggil.
Andi Bintaro.
- Andi Bintaro. - Saya.
Sarwendah!
Sarwendah!
Reno!
Reno!
Where's Sarwendah?
Sarwendah mana Sarwendah?
Mulyono Suparji.
Mulyono Suparji.
Are you Mulyono?
Kamu Mulyono?
He's Mulyono Suparji, son of an anchovy farmer.
Ini Mulyono Suparji. Anak tukang teri ini, Pak.
-Mackerel. -Son of a mackerel farmer, sir.
- Tongkol. - Anak tukang tongkol, Pak.
Come here.
Sini.
Dwi Adrianto.
Dwi Adrianto.
-Me, sir. -Sir…
- Saya, Pak. - Pak.
Just call me Franky.
Panggil Franky aja ya, Pak.
Mul-yo-no.
Mul-yo-no.
Come with me to the office.
Kamu ikut saya ke kantor.
Angga.
Angga.
Hendra.
Hendra.
Noval.
Noval.
Muhammad Fadhil.
Muhammad Fadhil.
You will work in my office.
Nanti kamu kerjanya di kantor saya.
I'll explain your tasks to you. Okay?
Nanti saya jelaskan tugasnya. Ya?
Okay.
Baik, Bu.
-Go on. -Forward!
- Ayo maju. - Jalan!
Good deeds
Perbuatan yang baik…
will bring you good rewards.
akan mendatangkan hal baik juga, Nak.
Oh, my God!
Astagfirullahaladzim!
Do you know, Dil?
Tahu enggak, Dil?
This factory
Pabrik ini…
caught on fire once.
dulu pernah kebakaran.
Where did you hear that?
Kamu tahu dari siapa?
Franky told me.
Franky yang cerita.
Really?
Masa sih, Mas?
Hang on.
Lo…
You all don't believe me?
Kalian pada enggak percaya?
It happened…
Kejadiannya…
Seven years ago.
Tujuh tahun yang lalu.
A big fire at the warehouse.
Kebakaran besar di gudang.
Everyone who was trapped…
Semua yang terjebak…
Died. Perished.
Mati.
They were all seasonal workers?
Buruh musiman semua?
That's right, Eko.
Ya, Mas Eko.
It was because
Gara-garanya,
they wandered outside at night.
mereka malam-malam kelayapan.
They were drunk.
Mabuk mereka.
Intoxicated.
Di bawah pengaruh alkohol.
How do you know they were drunk?
Tahu dari mana mereka mabuk?
That's what the rumors say.
'Kan katanya.
The warehouse was suddenly locked.
Gudang tiba-tiba terkunci.
And there was a big explosion. Boom!
Dan ada ledakan besar. Duar!
Bang!
Dor!
Boom!
Duar!
Everyone tried to escape, but they couldn't.
Semua berusaha keluar, tapi enggak bisa.
The fire started to spread.
Api mulai berkobar.
Those inside were burned alive.
Semua yang ada di dalam
They screamed.
Mereka teriak,
"It's hot!"
"Panas!"
After the incident,
Setelah kejadian itu,
the yellow and red hour rules were implemented.
dibuatlah aturan jam kuning dan jam merah.
Rumor has it,
Katanya, setiap malam…
their spirits wander around the factory.
arwah mereka gentayangan.
"Hot."
"Panas."
Nonsense!
Ngawur!
Wait.
Lo?
Why are you mad?
Kok marah?
Hey, where are you going?
Hei, mau ke mana? Hei.
Why are you running away? Boo! Coward!
Kok kabur?
Hendra!
Hendra!
-Damn you! -Scared, huh?
- Sialan! - Takut, ya?
Rani?
Mbak Rani?
Rani, what are you doing here?
Mbak Rani, sedang apa di sini?
Rani, I have a question.
Mbak Rani, aku mau tanya.
What do you want to ask?
Mau tanya apa?
Last night,
Tadi malam
did you slip out of the lodge?
Mbak Rani keluar dari loji?
Go back to your lodge and get some rest.
Langsung balik ke loji masing-masing ya, istirahat.
Endah? What's going on?
Loh, Endah? Kenapa, Endah?
What happened?
Ada apa?
Endah?
Mbak Endah?
Let's go back.
Ayo pulang.
Rani, just come with us.
Mbak Rani, ikut aja, enggak apa-apa.
Who wouldn't want to work at this factory?
Enak ya, Mas, kerja di pabrik ini.
Big salary.
Udah gajinya gede.
And we get a place to stay.
Terus dapat tempat tinggal.
Right.
Lah, iya.
But the locals don't want to work here anymore.
Tapi warga di sekitar pabrik 'kan udah enggak ada yang mau lagi kerja di sini.
That's why the factory hires people from other cities.
Makanya, pabrik nyari orang yang jauh-jauh.
Like you guys.
Yah, kayak kalian ini.
Because of the ghost sightings?
Karena banyak penampakan arwah?
Yes.
Ya.
The spirits of the fire victims.
Arwah korban kebakaran.
But there's something even scarier.
Selain arwah korban kebakaran, ada lagi yang lebih seram.
Back in colonial times, this factory had everything.
Dulu pabrik ini zaman kolonial ya, 'kan lengkap banget toh.
Tennis court, they had it.
Lapangan tenis, ada.
-School. -They had it.
- Sekolah. - Ada.
-Barbershop?
- Pangkas rambut, Mas?
-Beggars that walked backwards? -Sure.
- Pengemis mundur? - Ada.
It's common at a sugar factory. What else, Franky?
Pengemis mundur wajar di pabrik gula. Apa lagi, Franky?
I was just asking.
Orang cuma tanya toh, Mas.
Mental hospital? They had it.
Rumah sakit jiwa? Ada.
-What for? -For your friend here.
Rumah sakit jiwa buat apa?
Go on.
Lanjut.
But rumor has it,
Tapi kabarnya, ya
at this hour,
kalau jam-jam segini ini…
a spirit wanders around.
suka ada demit berkeliaran.
A mental hospital patient.
Ya itu, pasien rumah sakit jiwa.
She always appears
Dia itu kalau muncul
with her back to us.
selalu membelakangi kita.
If we turn our back and run away,
Kalau kita kabur balik badan,
she will reappear in front of us.
dia pasti muncul lagi depan kita.
If we run away again, she will reappear.
Kita kabur lagi
If we run away again…
Kita kabur lagi…
She will reappear.
Dia muncul lagi.
Hang on.
Tunggu.
What should we do then?
Terus kita harus apa?
You have to politely say…
Harus ada yang pamit.
"Excuse me."
"Permisi."
Only then will she leave.
Baru dia mau pergi.
Hear that? Even a ghost appreciates courtesy.
Nah. Demit aja menghargai sopan santun.
Enough!
Sudah!
Go back to your lodge.
Pada balik loji.
It's almost 9:00 p.m.
Ini sebentar lagi jam 21.00.
Red hour.
Udah mau jam merah.
Time for the spirits to wander about.
Jamnya demit keluyuran.
Don't forget.
Jangan lupa.
"Excuse me."
"Permisi."
Excuse me.
Permisi.
I'm not the ghost!
Hantunya bukan aku!
Dwi!
Dwi!
What's the hurry?
Kenapa cepat-cepat?
Come on!
Ayo!
You must've been circumcised by a jinn when you were little.
Orang kalau masih kecil disunat jin, yah kayak gini.
Coward!
Penakut!
Don't be so slow.
Jangan lama-lama!
Look at me.
Kayak aku gini loh.
Calm and relaxed.
Tenang, kalem.
In control of any situation.
Bisa mengendalikan situasi.
Hurry up, Franky!
Ayo cepetan, Franky!
Mulyono, wait!
Mulyono, tunggu!
Franky!
Franky!
Don't leave me, Franky!
Jangan cepat-cepat, Franky!
Mulyono! Franky! Open!
Mulyono! Franky! Buka!
What are you thinking about, Wati?
Apa yang kamu pikirkan, Wati?
Hendra.
Mas Hendra, Ning.
Is he burdened by my mother's request?
Sebenarnya dia keberatan tidak ya, dengan permintaan ibuku?
I feel bad.
Aku jadi tidak enak dengannya.
Maybe I should postpone the wedding.
Kutunda saja ya menikahnya?
I wouldn't feel good
Kasihan…
if he paid for everything.
Kalau semua harus pakai uang dia.
What would you do if you were me, Naning?
Kalau kamu jadi aku bagaimana, Naning?
If it was me,
Yah, kalau aku, kalau persiapannya belum matang, ya aku enggak menikah.
But that's me.
Tapi itu kalau aku, ya.
-Where are you going? -The bathroom.
- Mau ke mana? - Kamar mandi.
-Wanna come? -No.
- Mau ikut? - Enggak.
"No."
"Enggak."
What would you do if you were me, Endah?
Kamu kalau jadi aku gimana, Endah?
Endah?
Endah?
You've been daydreaming.
Melamun terus loh kamu.
What did you say, Wati?
Tadi kamu ngomong apa, Wati?
Are you okay?
Enggak apa-apa kamu?
Endah, if something happened, don't keep it to yourself.
Endah, kalau ada apa-apa, jangan dipendam sendiri.
Naning and I are here. Tell us. Okay?
Ada aku dan Naning. Cerita.
I'm okay.
Aku enggak apa-apa.
What were you saying about your wedding?
'Kan kamu yang lagi pusing soal nikahan.
What's going on?
Ada apa, Naning?
It's dark.
Gelap.
The light went out.
Lampunya konslet.
It did?
Kok bisa konslet?
It's fine.
Ini menyala.
In the name of Allah.
Bismillah.
Help.
Tolong.
Last night I heard Hendra…
- Ini aku tadi malam dengar, Hendra… - Kata siapa?
-Should I? -Ask him.
- Aku tanya, ya? - Tanya aja.
Hendra.
Hendra.
-What? -Were you dreaming last night?
- Apa? - Semalam kamu mimpi apa sih, Hendra?
I heard you talking in your sleep.
Aku dengar kamu mengigau.
You heard it?
Kedengaran toh?
I had a nightmare.
Ya, mimpi buruk aku.
Couldn't go back to sleep?
Enggak bisa tidur lagi, Hendra?
I couldn't.
Enggak bisa.
What did you dream about?
Mimpi apa kamu, Mas?
It was unclear.
Enggak jelas.
Tell me about it.
Cerita padaku kamu mimpi apa.
-Answer me, what did you dream about? -Forget about it!
Jawab, kamu mimpi apa?
I'm fine.
Aku enggak apa-apa.
Stop nagging.
Jangan begini, Wati.
It's embarrassing.
Tidak enak dengan yang lain.
We are here to work. That's it!
Kita di sini untuk kerja.
Don't listen to him.
Sudah enggak usah dipikirin.
It's fine, Wati.
Tenang, Wati.
Wati, it was just a dream.
Wati.
Don't make too much of it.
Enggak usah terlalu dipikirkan.
You're wrong.
Yah, enggak bisa gitu, Fadhil.
I can't stop thinking about my dream.
Kalau aku malah kepikiran terus.
Because it was a beautiful dream.
Lah semalam aku mimpi indah kok.
I dreamed about marrying Naning.
Mimpi nikah sama Dek Naning.
It was beautiful for you.
Bagimu mimpi indah.
For me, it's…
Bagiku mimpi bu…
-What? -Happy?
- Bu… - Buahagia?
Horrible!
Buruk!
Franky, from now on, don't sleep again.
- Franky. - Apa?
I feel for Naning.
Kasihan Naning.
Do you want me to die quickly, Dwi?
Loh, kamu pengin aku mati cepat, Dwi?
Not too quickly.
Loh enggak usah cepat-cepat.
Do it slowly.
Pelan-pelan aja.
So we can be prepared.
Biar bisa siap-siap.
Prepared, huh?
Oh, siap-siap ya, Dwi?
Let me check.
Biar saya cek dulu.
This one.
Yang ini…
Bring it to the weigh station.
Tolong dibawa ke stasiun timbang.
Yes, sir.
Baik, Pak.
-Thank you, sir. -Okay.
- Terima kasih, Pak. - Ya.
Endah.
Mbak Endah.
Hey, Rani.
Hei, Mbak Rani.
Where are you going?
Mau ke mana?
To deliver documents to the crane station and the weigh station.
Aku mau antar dokumen ke stasiun derek dan timbangan.
Let me help you.
Biar kubantu, ya, Mbak.
I'm on my way to the weigh station.
Aku juga sekalian mau ke stasiun timbangan.
It's okay, Rani, I can do it myself.
Tidak apa-apa, aku bisa sendiri.
It's okay. I'm heading there anyway.
Enggak apa-apa, Mbak, sekalian jalan.
Okay, then.
Ya sudah.
-Thanks. -Yes.
- Terima kasih, ya. - Ya.
-See you. -Take care.
- Aku duluan ya. - Hati-hati ya, Mbak.
Rani!
Mbak Rani!
Why didn't you bring the document yourself?
Kenapa bukan kamu sendiri yang antar dokumennya?
That was your job!
Itu tugasmu!
I'm sorry, ma'am.
Maaf, Bu.
Rani offered to help.
Tadi Mbak Rani yang menawari untuk bantu.
What's wrong with you?
Bagaimana sih kamu ini?
I'm sorry, ma'am. It's my fault.
Maaf, Bu. Saya salah.
Forgive me, ma'am.
Ampuni saya, Bu.
Now what?
Apa lagi?
What is it?
Apa, Mbah?
Ma'am.
Bu.
Shouldn't we postpone the milling?
Apa enggak sebaiknya penggilingan ditunda dahulu?
We can't.
Tidak bisa, Mbah.
I just reported to the higher-ups that everything is on track.
Saya baru lapor atasan kalau semuanya sedang dipersiapkan.
How can I ask for a postponement?
Masa sekarang minta mundur?
I need a little bit of time.
Saya perlu waktu sedikit.
Jinah and I need to make sure this is a normal work accident.
Saya dan Mbah Jinah harus memastikan ini kecelakaan kerja biasa.
The next Legi day is not until next week.
Hari Legi berikutnya itu masih minggu depan.
If we postpone, the loss will be too big.
Kalau ditunda, kerugiannya akan terlalu besar.
I'm sorry. It's out of the question.
Maaf, Mbah. Tidak mungkin.
This is too risky.
Ini sangat berisiko.
I think my hunch was right.
Firasatku sepertinya betul, Mbah!
It wasn't a normal accident.
Kejadian itu bukan kecelakaan biasa.
Calm yourself.
Tenangkan pikiranmu, Samin.
This afternoon, we have to prepare the offering ceremony.
Sore ini kita harus menyiapkan upacara persembahan.
What do you think made them angry?
Menurutmu apa yang membuat mereka marah?
I have no idea.
Aku tidak tahu.
All I know is
Yang penting,
we need to be calm in handling this.
kita harus tenang menghadapi ini.
Endah.
Endah.
Are you okay, Endah?
Kamu tidak apa-apa, Endah?
I heard about the accident.
Aku dengar soal kecelakaan tadi.
I'm scared.
Aku takut.
I'm afraid that it wasn't a normal accident.
Aku takut ini bukan kecelakaan biasa.
What do you mean?
Maksud kamu apa?
To be honest,
Sebenarnya…
I've been experiencing strange things here.
aku udah beberapa kali mengalami hal aneh di sini.
On our first night here,
Di malam pertama,
I went out of the lodge during the red hours.
aku keluar dari loji setelah jam merah.
Oh, dear. Does Mrs. Marni know?
Aduh.
No one knows except you. I don't want to get fired.
Enggak ada yang tahu selain kamu. Aku takut dipecat.
Endah…
Endah.
that night, who were you with?
Malam itu, kamu sama siapa?
I followed someone
Aku ikutin orang
who went out of the lodge to the factory.
yang keluar dari loji sampai ke pabrik.
But I lost track of that person.
Tapi aku kehilangan jejaknya.
That night…
Di malam itu…
I saw a wayang performance.
aku lihat pagelaran wayang.
In the factory?
Di pabrik?
Are you sure?
Kamu yakin, Ndah?
I feel like something is off.
Aku merasa ada yang janggal.
The accident had nothing to do with what I saw, right?
Kecelakaan tadi gak ada hubungannya sama apa yang kulihat, 'kan?
Endah.
Endah, sudah.
Right now, you need to calm yourself.
Saat ini, kamu tenangkan dirimu.
Be alert.
Tetap hati-hati.
Don't forget to pray.
Jangan lupa salat dan wudu.
Let's hope our offerings are accepted
Semoga apa yang kita persembahkan diterima.
and there'll be no more accidents.
Tidak ada lagi musibah terjadi.
Yes.
Ya, Mbah.
Rani?
Mbak Rani?
Excuse me.
Permisi, Mbak.
Rani, I want to apologize.
Mbak Rani, aku mau minta maaf.
I'm sorry.
Maaf, Mbak.
It was my mistake.
Aku salah tadi.
How are you feeling?
Mbak Rani gimana keadaannya?
Endah!
Endah!
Oh, my God!
Astagfirullahaladzim!
What happened?
Apa yang terjadi?
Ask forgiveness from Allah.
Istigfar, Endah.
Are you feeling guilty, Endah?
Kamu merasa bersalah ya, Endah?
Rani is fine.
Rani enggak apa-apa kok.
They've sent her home.
Tadi udah dianterin pulang.
Wati.
Wati.
Weren't you going to take this to Hendra?
Kamu bukannya mau anterin makanan buat Hendra?
It's almost 9:00 p.m.
Udah mau jam 21.00 loh ini.
I haven't put on my hijab.
Aku belum pakai kerudung lagi. Sebentar.
Let me do it.
Ya sudah, aku aja yang anterin.
-Do you mind? -No.
- Enggak apa-apa, Ning? - Enggak apa-apa.
Thank you.
Tolong ya.
Who is it?
Siapa itu?
Naning.
Dek Naning.
Is this a dream?
Ini mimpi bukan, ya?
Dwi!
Dwi!
-What is it, Franky? -Hit me, bro.
Apa sih, Franky?
Hey! What have you done?
Hei! Bagaimana sih?
Damn you!
Sialan!
Without any warning?
Kok tidak pakai aba-aba sih?
Again?
Sekali lagi?
But it's okay.
Tapi tidak apa-apa.
This isn't a dream, then.
Berarti ini bukan mimpi.
Look, Dwi.
Lihat, Dwi.
My effort is fruitful.
Usaha tidak akan mengkhianati hasil.
Naning came to see me.
Dek Naning loh yang nyamperin aku duluan.
Naning,
Dek Naning,
I didn't expect you to come to me.
aku tidak menyangka kamu mendatangi aku.
I also didn't expect Naning to be far-sighted.
Aku juga tidak menyangka.
-I'll poke your eyes out! -What's going on here?
Matamu!
Here, Wati asked me to bring this to you.
Ini loh, titipan makanan dari Wati.
-Thanks, Naning. -Okay.
- Terima kasih. - Ya.
Hendra, what do I have to do to be loved that much?
Hendra, bagaimana caranya biar bisa dicintai sebegitunya?
I lack nothing.
Aku loh enggak ada kurangnya.
You lack a shower, Franky.
Kau mesti mandi, Franky.
Dirty from head to toe.
Badanmu kotor semua.
Naning, the red hour alarm will go off soon.
Naning.
You're not allowed to be out of your lodge.
Sudah enggak boleh ada di luar loji.
Yes. Okay, then.
Ya. Ya sudah.
Hey, Naning.
Hei, Naning.
How is Endah?
Endah tidak apa-apa?
She's fine.
Enggak apa-apa.
-Good night, boys. -Naning.
- Ya sudah. Mari. - Dek.
Let me walk you back.
Aku anterin ya.
Take care of that nosebleed, why don't you?
Itu mimisan, diurusin dulu.
Hey!
Dek!
This is not a nosebleed.
Ini bukan mimisan.
This is the snort of a fool in love.
Ini ingusnya orang sedang jatuh cinta.
Naning!
Dek!
Wow, she walks so fast.
Wah kok ngebut sekali jalannya.
Wait…
Lho?
What's going on here? Why didn't they take the offerings?
Apa yang terjadi ini?
Looks like we have a ritual to perform.
Seharian ini kita harus tirakat.
I have a bad feeling about this.
Firasatku tidak enak.
Aren't you scared, Rano?
Kamu enggak takut, Rano?
Samin and Jinah's offerings weren't accepted.
Persembahannya Mbah Samin sama Mbah Jinah tidak diterima.
Maybe the spirits don't like beef.
Itu dia. Apa hantunya tidak suka sapi, ya?
They should try the trotters, it's the best part.
Padahal kalau kikilnya dimasak,
Stop joking about it. It can bring us bad luck.
Jangan bercanda.
A security guard shouldn't be superstitious.
Satpam kok takut takhayul.
Who's drawing water this late at night?
Siapa yang mandi malam-malam begini?
Maybe it's Jinah?
Mbah Jinah apa, ya?
Jinah!
Mbah Jinah!
It must be a ghost.
Setan ini sih.
Damn it!
Sialan!
Your baton!
- Aduh! - Pentungmu!
I'll get it tomorrow!
Besok aja!
Oh, my God!
Astagfirullah!
I'm late!
Telat aku!
-Rano! -Let's go.
- Rano! - Ayo, Mbah.
-Ma'am. -Where?
- Bu. - Di mana?
Jinah. Samin.
Mbah Jinah, Mbah Samin.
Postpone the milling, ma'am. Don't do it today.
Tunda penggilingannya, Bu.
Rano, Karno, come with me.
Rano, Karno. Ikut saya.
Yes, ma'am.
Siap, Bu.
Sir.
Mbah.
Oh, my God!
Astagfirullah!
He's from your village?
Dia teman sekampungmu?
No, sir.
Bukan, Mbah.
I think his name is Eko.
Setahu saya namanya Eko.
Do not cause panic.
Jangan bikin ramai.
Sorry, sir.
Maaf, Mbah.
I don't mean to be impudent,
Ini bukan bermaksud lancang, tapi…
but how could this happen?
itu kenapa bisa terjadi, Mbah?
Is this your first time here as a seasonal worker?
Kamu baru ini
You're not an ordinary guy.
Kamu bukan orang biasa.
What have you experienced here?
Apa yang sudah kamu alami di sini?
Don't hide what you know.
Jangan menyembunyikan apa yang kamu tahu.
It won't help with the situation.
Itu bisa membuat situasi lebih berbahaya.
Your hand, child.
Tanganmu, Nak.
What did you see that night?
Apa yang kamu lihat malam itu?
What's going on here, ma'am?
Kenapa ini, Mbah?
Be honest.
Jujur saja.
So it won't be painful.
Biar enggak sakit.
It's okay, Endah.
Tidak apa-apa, Endah.
They know.
Mbah Jinah dan Mbah Samin sudah tahu.
A wayang show, ma'am.
Pagelaran wayang, Mbah.
Why did you go there?
Buat apa kamu ke sana?
That night…
Malam itu…
I saw someone leave the lodge.
saya lihat ada seseorang yang keluar dari loji.
I tried to follow the person.
Saya coba kejar.
I thought it was one of my friends.
Saya pikir salah satu teman saya, Mbah.
But I lost them.
Tapi saya kehilangan jejak.
And then,
Kemudian,
I saw a crowd.
saya lihat ada keramaian.
Who was it?
Siapa yang keluar?
I don't know, ma'am.
Tidak tahu, Bu.
I'm sorry, all of you.
Maaf, Bu, Mbah.
Maybe it was Rani?
Apa mungkin Rani orangnya?
The worker who met with an accident.
Buruh yang kecelakaan kemarin itu.
I met Rani after the accident.
Saya sudah bertemu Rani setelah kecelakaan kemarin.
She's just another victim of the spirit's anger.
Dia hanya salah satu korban
Actually, the curfew was implemented
Sebenarnya, himbauan jam malam itu
so the workers don't see them.
supaya buruh-buruh tidak melihat mereka.
The inhabitants of this sugar factory.
Para penghuni kerajaan demit.
Just like what you saw at that wayang show.
Seperti yang kamu lihat
But
Tapi…
the reason the workers were harmed…
yang menyebabkan buruh-buruh celaka…
is not because you saw them.
bukan karena kamu melihat mereka.
There's a bigger violation that we don't know about yet.
Ada pelanggaran yang lebih besar lagi yang kita belum tahu.
You said something about a dream.
Tadi kamu bicara soal mimpimu.
What did you see?
Apa yang kamu lihat?
Someone with your ability…
Orang yang memiliki ilmu batin
their dreams usually reveal something.
kadang mendapat petunjuk lewat mimpi.
Your dream might be a clue.
Mimpimu bisa jadi sebuah petunjuk.
What did you dream about?
Kamu mimpi apa?
On the first night,
Di malam pertama,
I dreamed…
saya mimpi…
When Endah said that she left her lodge,
Saat Endah cerita ke saya
I thought it was her in my dream.
saya pikir yang di mimpi saya itu Endah.
Did you go to the west warehouse?
Kamu pergi ke gudang barat?
No, ma'am.
Tidak, Mbah.
I saw the wayang show
Saya lihat pagelaran itu
in the warehouse next to the main building.
di gudang yang ada di luar gedung utama.
That means there were two other people who went to the west warehouse.
Berarti ada dua orang lain yang ke gudang barat.
Maybe it was them who made the bigger violation.
Mungkin mereka yang membuat kesalahan lebih besar.
Jinah.
Mbah.
Are you sure this has something to do with the forbidden warehouse?
Si Mbah yakin
Forbidden warehouse?
Gudang terlarang?
This west warehouse is where the big fire happened.
Gudang barat ini tempat kebakaran besar terjadi waktu itu.
It is forbidden for anyone to enter the warehouse.
Gudang terlarang yang seharusnya tidak boleh didatangi lagi oleh siapa pun.
Humans and jinn live together on this land.
Manusia
We have promised to live harmoniously.
Janjinya
Whoever breaks the promise will die.
Siapa yang ingkar janji akan mati.
Die!
Mati!
Ma'am.
Mbah.
What is this place?
Ini sebenarnya tempat apa?
In the past, during the colonial era, accidents often happened here.
Dulu, pada zaman Belanda,
They finally made a pact with Maharatu,
Mereka akhirnya mengikat perjanjian dengan Maharatu,
Queen of the Spirit Kingdom,
pemimpin kerajaan demit,
to not bother each other.
agar tidak saling mengganggu.
Since then,
Sejak itu,
this warehouse has become a sacred place.
gudang ini menjadi tempat keramat.
Seven years ago,
Tujuh tahun lalu,
a group of seasonal workers
sekelompok buruh musiman
did something reckless here.
melakukan hal ceroboh di tempat ini.
That mistake angered the spirits
Kesalahan itu menyebabkan amarah penghuni kerajaan demit.
and a big fire broke out.
Sehingga kebakaran terjadi.
After that,
Setelah itu
this warehouse was closed completely.
gudang ini benar-benar ditutup.
I didn't expect someone would trespass…
Saya tidak menyangka
and break this supernatural barrier.
apalagi sampai merusak batas gaib ini.
Not only that,
Bukan itu saja.
someone has stolen Maharatu's belongings.
Ada yang mencuri benda milik Maharatu.
What belongings?
Ini sebenarnya yang dicuri apa toh?
I don't see anything.
Kok aku enggak lihat apa-apa, ya?
Only people with special abilities can see it.
Hanya orang-orang sakti yang bisa melihat ini.
What do you see?
Kamu sakti?
The thing is, I also don't see anything.
Nah itu masalahnya,
I knew it.
Oalah.
There was gold jewelry, invisible to the common eye,
Ada perhiasan-perhiasan emas tak kasat mata milik Maharatu.
But somehow, someone was able to see it and took it.
Dan entah bagaimana, seseorang bisa melihat,
We're in serious danger now.
Kita semua dalam bahaya besar sekarang.
-We-- -Jinah.
- Kita harus… - Mbah.
-Mrs. Marni. -Ma'am?
- Bu Marni. - Bu?
Mrs. Marni.
Bu Marni. Bu?
Ma'am.
Bu!
Rano, Karno,
Rano, Karno.
take her home.
Tolong antar Bu Marni ke rumahnya.
Yes, ma'am.
Ya, Mbah.
The missing gold
Perhiasan yang hilang dari tempat ini
was probably taken by the two people in your dream.
kemungkinan diambil oleh dua orang di mimpimu itu.
Please help me
Tolong bantu saya
find out who they are.
cari siapa mereka.
Yes, ma'am.
Ya, Mbah.
Let's go.
Ayo.
The door! Where is it?
Pintunya?
Endah?
Endah?
Endah!
Endah!
Wati!
Wati!
No!
Jangan!
Forgive me!
Ampun!
Hey, Naning!
Hei, Naning!
Hey!
Hei!
What happened?
Kamu kenapa?
Hey! Naning!
Hei! Naning!
It's all because of this!
Ini semua pasti gara-gara ini, Mas!
God damn you!
Sialan!
Why is this here? Huh?
Ini kenapa di sini?
I told you not to take it!
Aku udah bilang jangan diambil!
I couldn't resist!
Aku khilaf, Mas!
Damn it.
Udah.
We must return it.
Kita harus kembalikan.
If the others find out, we will be screwed!
Kalau sampai yang lain tahu, bisa mati kita!
Let's go!
Ayo!
Stop it. Come on!
Udah. Ayo!
What? You're scared?
Apa? Takut?
This is all your fault.
Ini semua 'kan karena kamu.
And now you're scared?
Kenapa sekarang kamu takut?
Naning!
Naning!
Naning, snap out of it.
Naning, sadar.
Let's go. Come on!
Ayo.
What were Endah and Fadhil doing in Mrs. Marni's house?
Endah sama Fadhil ke rumah Bu Marni, kenapa ya?
I don't know.
Enggak tahu.
Maybe it has something to do with Eko, the missing guy.
Apa jangan-jangan ada hubungannya sama Eko, yang hilang itu.
-Your workmate at the crane station? -Yep.
Eko, teman kerjamu di crane?
His roommate said he was in his room long before the red hours.
Padahal kemarin kata temannya sebelum jam merah masih ada di kamarnya loh.
Why is Hendra not back yet? He was getting Naning.
Mas Hendra panggil Naning kok enggak balik-balik, ya?
The food is getting cold.
Makanan udah keburu dingin.
-Franky, Dwi! -That's Fadhil and Endah.
Franky, Dwi!
Fadhil.
Fadhil.
Endah?
Endah?
Endah! Fadhil!
Endah! Fadhil!
What's going on? Where's Hendra?
Ini ada apa?
-Naning? -Hendra?
- Naning? - Mas Hendra?
-Hendra! -Naning!
- Hendra! - Naning!
Naning!
Naning!
Are you sure Hendra and Naning aren't at the lodge?
Kalian yakin Hendra dan Naning tidak ada di loji?
They aren't there.
Tidak ada.
We were just there.
Kan kami baru dari sana.
The two people in your dream, were they a man and a woman?
Fadhil, di mimpimu, dua orang itu laki-laki dan perempuan?
Maybe Hendra and Naning did it.
Jangan-jangan, Hendra dan Naning pelakunya.
Hang on.
Tunggu.
Did what?
Ini pelaku apa?
What is happening?
Sebenarnya ada apa?
Whose gold is this?
Ini emas siapa?
And why did you get called to Mrs. Marni's house?
Terus kalian dipanggil ke rumah Bu Marni kenapa?
It's a long story.
Ceritanya panjang, Dwi.
One thing's for sure,
Yang pasti,
all the strange happenings here are because someone stole this.
semua kejadian aneh di sini terjadi itu karena ada yang mencuri ini.
This is sacred, it belongs to the spirits.
Ini barang keramat penunggu pabrik.
Spirits?
Penunggu?
-You mean ghosts? -Hang on.
- Demit, maksudmu? - Tunggu.
What are you talking about?
Ini maksudnya apa?
Stole what?
Curi apa?
Are you accusing Hendra and Naning of stealing?
Kamu menuduh Mas Hendra dan Naning mencuri?
Based on your dream?
Hanya berdasarkan mimpimu, Fadhil?
Hendra would never steal anything.
Enggak mungkin Mas Hendra mencuri.
Let's go find them.
Ayo cari mereka.
We still have time before the red hours.
Masih ada waktu sebelum jam merah.
Dwi, Franky.
Dwi, Franky.
Find Rano and Karno. Ask them to help us.
Coba kalian cari Mas Rano dan Mas Karno.
Okay?
Ya?
Endah.
Endah.
Please go back to the west warehouse.
Tolong, kamu ke gudang barat lagi.
Bring that gold and tell Jinah that our two friends are missing.
Bawa perhiasan emas itu dan bilang sama Mbah Jinah kalau dua teman kita hilang.
And where are you going to go?
Terus kamu ke mana?
I'll search the lodges.
Aku keliling di loji-loji.
Maybe someone saw Hendra and Naning.
Siapa tahu
Fadhil, I'm going with you.
Fadhil, aku ikut kamu ya.
Wait. Dwi?
Loh. Dwi?
-Fadhil! Can I? Please? -What's wrong?
- Fadhil! Ya 'kan? - Apa sih?
Let's go.
Ayo.
I should go with Fadhil.
Mending aku ikut Fadhil.
Forget him. You're safer with me. I know this area best.
Ikut Fadhil? Ikut aku. Aku yang paling menguasai daerah ini.
Help. My friend is inside.
Tolong. Teman saya di dalam, Mas.
Your friend?
Temanmu?
-Help. -What's going on?
- Tolong, Mas. - Kenapa?
Help. In here.
Tolong, Mas. Di dalam sini, Mas.
In there. In that room.
Di sini, Mas. Di kamar ini.
Help.
Tolong, Mas.
Just go in.
Masuk aja, Mas.
Peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Sir?
Mas?
The one outside?
Yang di luar?
The one outside isn't human.
Yang di luar itu bukan manusia.
I seek refuge in Allah from the outcast Satan.
Auzubillah minashaitan nirajeem.
Oh, my God.
Astagfirullahaladzim.
Sir?
Mas?
Naning?
Naning?
Hendra?
Hendra?
Naning!
Naning!
Hendra!
Hendra!
Why are you mimicking me? Your tone is exactly the same as mine.
Kok kamu ikut-ikut aku terus?
Well, all you do is call for Naning.
Yah, kamu manggil-manggil Naning terus kok.
So what?
Memangnya kenapa?
Judging from past experience,
Kalau tampangmu yang kayak binturong gini manggil Naning,
Not always!
Kebanyakan teori!
But, okay.
Ya sudah.
-Hendra! -Naning!
- Hendra! - Naning!
Hendra!
Hendra!
Naning!
Naning!
Damn it!
Sialan!
He's got a hole in his face!
Hantu wajah bolong!
Mulyono, wait for me!
Mulyono! Tunggu!
There's no way. Hendra is not a thief.
Enggak mungkin Mas Hendra mencuri, Endah.
Endah!
Endah!
This place is not right.
Tempat ini itu aneh.
Wait here, okay?
Tunggu di sini dulu ya, Mas.
Franky, wait for me!
Franky, tunggu aku!
Franky!
Franky!
What now?
Kenapa, Franky?
I'll count to 17.
Aku hitung sampai 17.
And then we run, okay?
Kita kabur, ya.
Not 17. I'll wet myself before then.
Jangan 17.
One, two…
Satu, dua…
Seventeen!
- Tujuh belas! - Franky!
Franky.
Franky.
remember what Karno said?
Ingat enggak yang diceritain Mas Karno?
He said if we didn't politely excuse ourselves, she wouldn't go away.
Katanya kalau kita enggak pamit, dia enggak akan pergi, Franky.
Hurry up and do it then!
Ayo cepetan kamu pamit!
Why me?
Kok aku?
You're in front.
- Kamu terlanjur di depan kok. - Loh.
Franky!
Enggak mau, Franky! Enggak!
Just do it, Dwi!
Ayo, Dwi!
Miss…
Mbak.
excuse me.
Permisi.
My apologies.
Maaf.
Good evening.
Selamat malam.
She's not responding. Franky!
Diam dia, Franky!
Not every ghost originates from Java.
Enggak semua demit asalnya dari Jawa.
Try again!
Coba lagi, Dwi!
Miss…
Mbak.
peace be upon you.
Asalamualaikum.
Franky, you do it.
Franky, kamu aja.
Dwi!
Dwi!
Miss…
Mbak.
excuse me.
Maaf, Mbak.
It's not that we're arrogant,
Bukannya kami sombong
or don't want to chat with you,
atau enggak mau ngobrol.
-but we're very busy. -That's right.
- Tapi kami ada kesibukan, Mbak. - Ya, Mbak.
Excuse…
Permi…
Dwi,
Dwi.
did she just wet herself?
Kok demitnya malah mengompol?
I think the ghost is scared of you.
Kayaknya demitnya takut sama kamu.
Hey!
Hei!
Dwi! Franky!
Dwi! Franky!
Damn you!
Sialan!
You startled us!
Kagetin aja kamu, Fadhil!
Have you found Naning and Hendra?
Kalian sudah ketemu Naning dan Hendra?
Not yet, but we found a ghost who wet herself.
Naning dan Hendra, belum.
When the ghost saw Franky, she--
Jadi, ceritanya, pas demitnya ketemu Franky, dia…
Where else are you going?
Sekarang mau ke mana lagi?
I'm going to the west warehouse.
Aku mau langsung ke gedung barat.
I'm scared for Endah and Wati.
Aku takut Endah dan Wati kenapa-kenapa.
Okay, then.
Ya udah.
Let's not split up again.
Yang penting kita jangan berpencar lagi.
-Come. -Fadhil, in front.
- Ayo. - Fadhil, di depan.
Let's go.
Ayo.
Sir.
Mas.
Where are you going?
Kalian ini mau ke mana?
It's red hour.
Ini sudah jam merah.
We want to…
Kami mau…
return something.
mengembalikan barang, Mas.
All right, go ahead.
Ya udah sana.
Thank you.
Makasih, Mas.
Excuse me.
Permisi, Mas.
Rano?
Rano.
Are they the thieves?
Apa itu pencurinya?
Jinah has got some serious magic.
Mbah Jinah memang sakti sekali.
We haven't even looked for the thieves, but they're already turning themselves in.
Kita belum sempat mencari pencurinya,
Imagine if Ms. Jinah was a cop.
Kalau Mbah Jinah jadi polisi
Jails would be full.
penjara penuh.
She would make a super policewoman.
Mbah Jinah kok polisi, polwan.
But she'd be too old, I think.
Tapi ketuaan kayaknya.
This is not everything.
Ini belum semuanya.
Ma'am…
Mbah.
I found this at the lodge.
Ini ada di teras loji.
Did you steal this?
Kamu mencuri, Mas?
Huh?
Hah?
Why did you have to steal?
Kenapa harus mencuri, Mas?
Because of my mother's demands?
Karena tuntutan Ibu?
Just forget about the wedding reception!
Mas, kita enggak usah bikin hajatan, enggak apa-apa, Mas!
Oh, God!
Ya Allah!
What did you do here
Apa yang sudah kalian lakukan di tempat ini
that gave you the ability to see Maharatu's belongings?
sampai kalian bisa melihat barang-barang milik Maharatu?
It's better for you to come clean.
Lebih baik kalian jujur.
This can bring harm to everyone.
Ini bisa membahayakan semua orang.
Including both of you.
Termasuk kalian berdua.
What did you do?
Apa yang sudah kalian lakukan?
On the first night,
Pada malam pertama
we came to this factory…
kami datang ke pabrik ini…
We…
kami…
I hate this.
Sebal aku.
Why did Wati have to come here?
Wati kok jadi ikut kerja?
It makes it hard for us. Have to meet discreetly, late at night.
Kita 'kan jadi susah, kalau ketemu gini, malam-malam, diam-diam.
But this is more exciting, right?
Tapi lebih seru begini, 'kan?
Don't mind her.
Sudahlah.
Stop making a long face.
Berhenti merengut seperti itu.
You have a pretty face.
Nanti hilang cantiknya.
Naning?
Naning?
Hey.
Hei.
Hey, Naning!
Hei. Naning!
Naning!
Naning!
Hendra, look.
Mas, lihat.
Hey! Don't take it!
Hei! Jangan diambil! Hei!
I have a bad feeling about this.
Perasaan aku enggak enak loh.
This place is strange.
Tempat ini aneh.
Come on, let's just go back.
Sudah, balik saja.
You know! You know she's my best friend!
Kamu tahu, Mas! Kamu tahu dia sahabatku!
Naning! You know I'm going to marry him!
Naning! Kamu tahu dia calon suamiku!
Oh, God!
Astaghfirullah!
How could you?
Teganya?
You piece of shit!
Sialan kamu!
You know how much I like Naning.
Kamu kan tahu,
And you had to have her, too?
Tetap saja kamu sikat!
You're engaged to be married!
Kamu itu punya calon istri!
You committed a sin in this place.
Kalian melakukan perbuatan dosa di tempat ini.
That gave you the ability to see Maharatu's gold.
Itu membuat kalian bisa melihat perhiasan emas milik Maharatu.
That's because adultery is Satan's favorite sin.
Itu karena zina
And it will open the gate to other sins.
Yang bisa membuka pintu-pintu dosa lainnya.
I thought all of this happened because of me.
Aku pikir semua karena aku.
It was you all along!
Ternyata kamu Ning!
Forgive me.
maafin aku.
I'm sorry.
Aku minta maaf, ya, Endah.
Wati.
Wati.
It's my fault.
Aku yang salah.
Don't!
- Jangan! - Wati…
Wati!
Wati!
-Wati!
- Wati!
Rano, what's happening to her?
Rano, kenapa dia?
Help me hold them off!
Bantu pegang mereka!
Hurry!
Cepat!
Wati…
Wati…
Endah?
Endah?
A long time ago,
Pada zaman dahulu
this was a sacred place.
tempat ini adalah tempat yang keramat.
A quiet and dense forest.
Hutan lebat sepi sunyi.
Animals came and died.
Apabila hewan berada di sana akan mati.
Men came, and only their names would leave the place.
Apabila manusia di sana akan pulang tinggal nama.
However,
Tetapi…
after greedy humans came,
Sesudah datangnya orang serakah di dunia ini
the beautiful shady trees
pohon-pohon rindang nan indah
And that became a huge problem.
Sehingga menjadi perkara besar.
Therefore,
Maka dari itu,
don't blame the ancestors for asking for a human blood sacrifice!
jangan salahkan apabila leluhur
The offerings.
Sesajennya.
The bride and groom.
Pengantinnya.
Are you okay?
Enggak apa-apa, Mas?
Endah?
Endah?
Endah! Oh, God!
Endah! Astagfirullah!
Endah.
Endah.
We have to prepare them, Jinah.
Kita harus segera menyiapkan mereka, Mbah.
We have no other choice.
Kita enggak punya pilihan lain.
They took advantage of this incident to demand another human sacrifice.
Mereka memanfaatkan ini untuk minta kembali pengantin tebu.
You're right.
Kamu benar.
We should comply with the spirits' demands.
Kita harus mengikuti permintaan kerajaan demit.
Or everyone's lives will be in danger.
Atau keadaan akan menjadi bahaya untuk semuanya.
They have to be sacrificed.
Mereka harus dikorbankan.
They're the bride and groom the spirits have chosen.
Mereka tumbal pengantin yang diinginkan.
-What? -Ma'am.
- Tumbal gimana, Mbah? - Mbah.
Forgive me, ma'am.
Ampun, Mbah.
We know we made a mistake.
Kami sadar kami salah, Mbah.
We will do anything.
Apa pun akan kami lakukan.
But don't make us the sacrifice.
Asalkan jangan jadi tumbal, Mbah.
I don't want to die, ma'am.
Aku enggak mau mati, Mbah!
Help us.
Tolong, Mbah.
Forgive me.
Ampun, Mbah.
-Rano. -Yes, ma'am.
- Rano. - Ya, Mbah?
Take them to Mrs. Marni's house.
Antar mereka ke rumah Bu Marni.
Tell Mrs. Marni they have to be prepared as the sugarcane ritual bride and groom.
Sampaikan pada Bu Marni
Yes, ma'am.
Ya, Mbah.
Karno.
Karno.
Help me prepare the ritual.
Bantu saya menyiapkan arak-arakan.
-Okay. -Let's go.
- Baik, Mbah. - Ayo.
Wait!
Mbah, tunggu!
Is there no other way, ma'am?
Mbah, apa enggak ada cara lain, Mbah?
Wati!
Wati!
You saw it yourself, didn't you?
- Kamu tadi melihatnya langsung toh? - Tunggu!
The sugarcane wedding ritual.
Ada arak-arakan manten tebu.
Your two friends have to become the bride and groom.
Kedua temanmu ini yang sekarang harus jadi mantennya.
Why do we have to comply with the spirits' demand?
Masa iya kita harus ikutin kemauannya demit, Mbah?
Since this sugar factory was built,
Sejak awal pabrik gula ini berdiri,
before every milling started,
setiap memulai masa giling,
the sugarcane wedding ritual has been conducted.
pabrik akan mengadakan ritual manten tebu.
Wati!
Wati!
Ma'am, forgive me!
Mbah, ampun! Mbah!
A couple is paraded to be buried in the sugarcane field
Sepasang manusia diarak untuk dikuburkan di ladang tebu
as offerings to the original inhabitants of this land.
sebagai persembahan kepada penghuni tanah ini.
The ruler of the Spirit Kingdom.
Penguasa kerajaan demit.
Let's pray.
Kita berdoa, ya.
And hope this is for the best.
Semoga ini yang terbaik.
We tried everything
Kami melakukan segala cara
so we wouldn't have to sacrifice humans anymore.
agar tidak lagi harus mengorbankan manusia
Until finally,
sampai akhirnya
they accepted a pair of oxen and other offerings
mereka menerima sepasang lembu dan sesajen
as a replacement.
sebagai gantinya.
Unfortunately,
Sayangnya,
the mistakes that your friends made
kesalahan yang kedua temanmu lakukan
has resulted in the demand for the sugarcane wedding ritual again
membuat mereka meminta kembali ritual manten tebu
with human sacrifice.
dengan tumbal manusia.
This is our offering to you.
Persembahan dari kami untukmu, Dalboh.
The offerings.
Sesajennya.
These are the two humans that have committed the biggest sin.
Inilah kedua orang yang hidup dalam kesalahan paling besar.
Forgive us, Maharatu.
Ampunilah kami, Maharatu.
Accept our offerings.
Terimalah persembahan ini.
The bride and groom.
Pengantinnya.
Mr. Samin.
Mbah…
They must stay inside the salt circle during the ritual.
Mereka tidak boleh keluar dari lingkaran garam
I cannot believe
Aku enggak menyangka
they sacrificed humans back then.
dulu manusia yang dikorbankan kayak gini.
Endah, Dwi, let's go.
Endah, Dwi.
Wati…
Wati…
If you don't want me anymore, I understand.
Kalau kamu enggak mau menerima Mas lagi, enggak apa-apa.
I just hope
Mas hanya berharap
that one day you can forgive me.
suatu hari nanti kamu bisa maafkan Mas.
I pray you will always be happy, Wati,
Mas doakan kamu akan selalu bahagia, Wati,
with whoever you marry in the future.
dengan siapa pun itu nanti.
I only ask for your forgiveness, Wati.
Mas hanya minta ampun, Wati.
I hate myself for letting you down.
Mas benci mengecewakanmu, Wati.
Wati!
Wati!
-Wati! -Forgive us, Wati!
- Wati! - Ampun, Wati!
Wati!
Wati!
Wati.
Wati…
Have they completed the ritual?
Kira-kira ritualnya sudah selesai belum ya, Bu?
This is our first time.
Ini pertama kalinya kami melakukan ritual ini.
Wati…
Wati…
Wati?
Wati?
What's going on?
- Ada apa? - Hendra!
-Open up! -What is this?
- Buka! - Ada apa ini?
-Hendra! -Open!
- Hendra! - Buka!
Hendra!
Mas Hendra!
Why is the door closed?
Kenapa pintunya tertutup?
Help! Just break down the door!
Tolong! Dobrak!
-Naning! -Hendra!
- Mbak Naning! - Hendra!
Open! Break down the door!
Buka! Dorong!
Come on, push the door harder!
Dorong lebih keras!
Wati!
Wati!
What's going on?
- Ada apa? - Wati!
-Hendra! -Naning!
- Hendra! - Naning!
Move!
Awas!
Come on, Rano!
Ayo, Rano!
The field.
Ladang.
Let's go!
Ayo!
-What's going on? -Let's go, Wati!
- Apa? - Ayo, Wati!
Stop the ritual!
Jangan diteruskan!
Stop, Ms. Jinah!
Hentikan, Mbah!
Move! Ms. Jinah!
Awas! Mbah Jinah!
Move!
Awas!
What's going on here?
Ada apa ini?
-Naning! -Hendra!
- Naning! - Hendra!
Naning!
Naning!
Human's dirty trickery
Tipu muslihat manusia
cannot deceive Maharatu!
tidak dapat memperdaya sang Maharatu!
Naning!
Naning!
-Naning! -Hendra!
- Naning! - Hendra!
Get them out!
Angkat!
Naning!
Naning!
We came here full of hope,
Kami berangkat dengan harapan besar.
only to return full of grief.
Tapi pulang membawa duka.
Our two best friends lost their lives.
Dua sahabat kami kehilangan nyawa.
In the end, there was nothing I could do,
Akhirnya tak ada yang bisa kulakukan
but to take this as a lesson.
kecuali menjadikan semua ini pelajaran.
Those who sow will reap.
Siapa yang menabur akan menuai.
Those who do wrong will have to pay the price.
Siapa yang berbuat harus bertanggung jawab.
We are sorry
Maaf,
that we were unable to save your friends.
kami tidak bisa menolong teman kalian.
Just like good deeds will bring you good rewards,
Seperti kebaikan mendatangkan kebaikan,
bad deeds result in punishment.
perbuatan buruk juga mendatangkan ganjaran.
Let's hope they're at peace on the other side.
Semoga mereka tenang di sana.